Preliminary Guide to the Business Division records, 1938-1948
University Archives Duke University
Business Division records 1938-1948
Duke University. Business Division.
15 Linear Feet
University Archives, Duke University.
Contains the records of the Business Division of Duke University. A. S. Brower was an administrative assistant (1939-1946), then business manager and comptroller of the Business Division (1946-1956). This position is now known as the Office of the Executive Vice President, part of Duke University Administration. Types of materials include memoranda, forms, correspondence, printed matter, blueprints, contracts, financial materials, and Southern Association of Colleges and Schools reports. Major subjects include Duke University Administration, the Business Division, history of the Office of the Executive Vice President, World War II and education, Selective Service, ROTC and V-12 military training programs, Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, and campus development and construction. Materials range in date from 1938 to 1948. Contains restricted materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
Boxes 1-7; Gift; 1995; A64-57
Box 8; Transfer; Budgets and Measurements Department; 1982; A82-121
Boxes 9-10; Transfer; Office of the Business Manager; 1967; A67-82
Historical Note
The Business Division of Duke University coordinated the financial and administrative business of schools and departments throughout Duke University.
During World War II, the Business Division mediated requests for student records and information pertaining to students enrolling (or deferring enrollment) in the Selective Service. The Business Division was also associated with some construction and building improvements on campus, particularly those of the Arts Center and East Campus buildings. The Business Division maintained contracts for these and other projects during the 1960s.
A. S. (Alfred Smith) Brower was a longtime staff member of the Business Division. Before coming to Duke University, Brower held several state government posts in finance and statistics, and was the Comptroller at North Carolina State University. From 1939 to 1946, Brower was administrative assistant in the Business Division. He then became the business manager and comptroller (now treasurer), serving in that position from 1946 until 1956. From 1956 to 1959, he served as the Business Division's business manager and treasurer. Brower died in 1968 at age 76.
In 1962, the Business Division was reorganized and renamed. The newly-formed Business and Finance Division was headed by the Vice President for Business and Finance, who was the chief fiscal officer of the university and reported to the president.
Collection Overview
Contains memoranda, forms, correspondence, printed matter, blueprints, contracts, financial materials, and Southern Association of Colleges and Schools reports pertaining to the Business Division at Duke University. A. S. Brower was an administrative assistant (1939-1946), then business manager and comptroller of the Business Division (1946-1956). Major subjects include Duke University Administration, the Business Division, history of the Office of the Executive Vice President, World War II and education, Selective Service, ROTC and V-12 military training programs, Southern Association of Colleges and Schools. and campus development and construction. Materials range in date from 1938 to 1948. Boxes 1 and 2 contain restricted materials.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Brower, A. S.
Duke University -- Administration
Duke University. Business Division
Duke University. Business Manager
Duke University. Controller
Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools (U.S.)
United States. Selective Service System. North Carolina
United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps
United States. Navy Dept. V-12 Program -- History
World War, 1939-1945 -- Education and the war
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - "Affidavit of College or University" forms (Box 1)
    Contains statements of student's intent to enlist in the service, or to defer enlistment in order to continue education at Duke University.
  - Correspondence regarding students, selective service, and education, ca. 1941-1943
    Student selective service correspondence is RESTRICTED.
  - Classification advice forms to Duke University from the Selective Service, ca. 1941-1943
    Classification forms are RESTRICTED.
  - "Affidavit of College or University" forms (Box 2)
  - Correspondence regarding students, selective service, and education, ca. 1941-1943
  - Classification advice forms to Duke University from the Selective Service, ca. 1941-1943
  - National Roster Survey (draft status of students enrolled in courses), 1944
  - Army Air Forces--Air ROTC proposal, 1946
  - Class of 1912 reunion (A. S. Brower was chair) and 1946 commencement materials
  - A Study of Academic Degrees Held by Members of the Duke University Faculty, 1937
  - Correspondence and conference materials from professional education organizations, 1940-1942 (Box 3)
  - Enrollment statistics of armed forces veterans, 1947-1948
  - Proposed school of aviation at Duke University, 1944
  - Clippings and bulletins, 1942
  - Letter to students from President Flowers, regarding students' decision to enroll in the draft, 1941
  - Selective Service questionnaire sent to all Duke University students, 1941
  - Selective Service registration information for students, 1941
  - Duke Council for American Defense, 1940-1941
  - Statistical report, enrollment of undergraduate men, March-June semester, 1944
  - Statistical report, enrollment of undergraduate men, November-January, 1944-1945
  - Statistical report, enrollment of undergraduate men, July 1943
  - Statistical report, enrollment of undergraduate men, Trinity College and College of Engineering, 1942-1943
    Includes dates of departure and military classification
  - Report of a meeting on the impact of the war on education, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Civilian morale
  - Labor supply
  - Materials for developing a war training program at a college or university, ca. 1941-1943
  - Student questionnaire, 1941
  - Statistical report on Selective Service status of Duke University students, 1941-1942
  - National Roster of Scientific and Specialized personnel (of Duke University)
  - Civilian Personnel Administration for the Army Air Forces, proposal and cancellation, 1945
  - Marine Corps recruiting, 1942
  - U.S. Coast Guard recruiting, 1942
  - Signal Corps recruiting, 1942-1947
  - Army recruiting and brochures
  - Joint Army-Navy Coast Guard recruiting and brochures
  - Navy Medical Specialist Unit, 1940
  - Proposed Navy Aviation Reception Center, 1942
  - Naval Supply Corps
  - Navy V-7
  - Navy V-5 Air Corps
  - Navy V-12 bulletins and general information, 1942-1943
  - Army enlisted reserve corps plan
  - Selective service registration, 1942
  - General correspondence regarding the draft, ca. 1941-1942
  - Fort Bragg conference on rehabilitation, 1941 (Box 5)
  - War Service Opportunities for College and University Students bulletins, 1941-1942
  - Navy V-1, correspondence, miscellaneous materials
  - War Advisory Council
  - A Report on War Courses Offered by Collegiate Schools of Business and Departments of Economics, 1942
  - List of veterans enrolled, spring, 1948
  - Army Finance School rosters, 1944
  - National Municipal League, correspondence and conference notes
  - Naval ROTC bulletins, 1943-1946
  - Civil defense organizations, general notes
  - Enrollment, 1945-1946
  - War Manpower Commission correspondence and reports, ca. 1942-1943
  - Article by A. S. Brower on annual earnings for the state of North Carolina, ca. 1937-1938
  - Student and faculty deferment materials (Box 6)
  - Duke Committee on Defense
  - Post-war planning, correspondence, 1943
  - Army (Box 7)
  - Finance School, contract W2287, 1942
  - Finance School, correspondence
  - Specialized Training Program in Medicine, correspondence and establishment materials, 1943-1946
  - Specialized Training Program in Medicine, contract W54 (SCIV)
  - Navy V-12
  - Medical ROTC, contract and correspondence, 1943-1946, 1963
  - Navy Theological School, contract and correspondence, 1944
  - Duke University prospectus sent to Navy
  - Commissioning expense reports, 1943-1944
  - Contract and correspondence, 1943, 1944-1946
  - Correspondence, 1943-1943
  - Reports and memoranda, 1943-1946
  - Textbook cost and appraisal
  - Contracting visit information, 1944
  - Correspondence on establishment, 1940-1941
  - Correspondence, 1946-1948
  - Correspondence on establishment of Transportation and Medical Corps, 1937-1940, 1946-1947
  - Association of NROTC Colleges, correspondence, 1947-1948
  - Veterans' rehabilitation training
  - Report, Recommendations for Organizing the Business Administration Division, 1948
  - Report, Establishment of Budgetary Control Program, 1948
  - Budgets and Measurements, budget book, 1950/1951 (Box 8)
  - Budgets and Measurements, budget book, 1960/1961, [2 folders]
  - Budget materials, 1960-1961 (Box 9)
  - Building and Grounds Committee materials, 1962
  - Child Psychiatry Rehabilitation Center, photographs and correspondence, 1962
  - Department of Music budget, 1963-1964
  - Divinity School renovation correspondence
  - Fallout shelter program, 1963
  - Fundraising Potentials for Duke University, 1962
  - Landscaping and the Duke Gardens, 1962
  - Manager of Store Operations, supervisor manual
  - Married student housing
  - Medical Center additions
  - Phytotron Road improvements
  - Outside audit, 1961-1962
  - Self-study reports for various departments, 1965
  - Space allocation Committee
  - Tuition grant program for children of staff members
  - Organization for Business and Finance, report and diagram, 1965
Related Material
Vice President for Business and Finance records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Business and Finance Division records.
University Archives, Duke University.